E.W. Blatchford collection on Charles G. Hammond, 1843, 1877-1913.
Congregational Library & Archives
E.W. Blatchford collection on Charles G. Hammond, 1843, 1877-1913.
1843 1913
MS4982
Congregational Library & Archives
.22 Cubic Feet
(1 box)
Charles Goodrich Hammond was born in Bolton, Connecticut on June 4, 1804. He was the eldest son of Chester and Fanny Goodrich Hammond. Charles was elected Auditor General of the State of Michigan for a time and then as the collector of the port of Detroit. In 1852, he became the Chicago manager for the Michigan Central Railroad and remained intimately connected with the city for the rest of his life. He died on April 15, 1884. Eliphalet Wickes (E.W.) Blatchford was born on May 31, 1826 in Stillwater, New York. His parents were the Rev. John Blatchford and Frances Wickes Blatchford. He served as the president of the Chicago Theological Seminary for over 40 years and as vice president of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. E.W. died in Chicago on January 14th, 1915. In 1852, E.W. Blatchford became friends with Charles G. Hammond. The two remained close friends until Hammond's death in 1884. Following his death, Blatchford worked closely with Hammond's brother, H.L. Hammond on the creation of a memorial biography. This collection contains records related to that memorial biography and includes drafts, correspondences, photographs, obituaries, and an autobiographical sketch.
Blatchford, E.W. (Eliphalet Wickes), 1826-1914
Hammond, Charles G.
Hammond, H. L. (Henry Laurens), 1815-1893
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library by the Chicago Theological Seminary in 2011; 2011-20.
Biographical Note
Charles Goodrich Hammond was born in Bolton, Connecticut on June 4, 1804. He was the eldest son of Chester and Fanny Goodrich Hammond. A few years later, the family moved to Smyrna in New York. His father helped establish a new church in the community and Charles would be converted in 1816 at the age of twelve. Charles was educated locally and also began teaching others, including in Whitesboro, New York. In 1825, Charles moved to Canandaigua and worked in a mercantile business. Charles met his wife, Charlotte, in Whitesboro and they were married in August 1827. They remained active members of Whitesboro until they moved to Detroit in 1834. While in Detroit, they joined the Presbyerian church and Charles was elected an elder. Charles, along with others, helped the building up of Union City, Michigan in 1836. His parents would join him at a farm they jointly purchased that same year. His father would eventually become a deacon for a church started in the area. Charles was elected Auditor General of the State of Michigan for a time and then as the collector of the port of Detroit. In 1852, he became the Chicago manager for the Michigan Central Railroad and remained intimately connected with the city for the rest of his life. He worked for other railroads until 1865, when his health began to fail. He took a few years off, exploring Europe, and by 1870 was back in Chicago where he would live for the rest of his life. In 1875, he withdrew from most business practices and focused on city and church life. He died on April 15, 1884.
Eliphalet Wickes (E.W.) Blatchford was born on May 31, 1826 in Stillwater, New York. His parents were the Rev. John Blatchford and Frances Wickes Blatchford. The Blatchfords moved to Chicago and then later to Missouri where John Blatchford served as president of Marion College. E.W. Blatchford returned to Illinois in 1845 to attend Illinois College. After college, he started and eventually achieved enough success with his lead and linseed oil manufacturing company to buy out his partner and reorganize the company as E.W. Blatchford and Company. In 1858, he married Mary Emily Williams and the two had seven children together. Throughout his life, Blatchford was a noted philanthropist and leading Congregational layperson. He served as the president of the Chicago Theological Seminary for over 40 years and as vice president of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, devoting himself greatly to missionary work. He also played a central role in establishing the Newberry Library in Chicago, where the majority of his family papers now reside. E.W. died in Chicago on January 14th, 1915.
In 1852, Blatchford became friends with Charles G. Hammond. The two remained close friends until Colonel Hammond's death in 1884. From the late 1880's onward, Blatchford worked closely with Hammond's brother, H.L. Hammond on the creation of a memorial biography, "The Memorabilia of Charles G. Hammond", which was completed in 1889.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records related to E.W. Blatchford and his goal of creating a memorial biography for Charles G. Hammond. This includes drafts, correspondences, photographs, obituaries, and an autobiographical sketch.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically by date.
Related Materials
Additional records related to E.W. Blatchford can be found in the Blatchford family papers located at the Newberry Library, Chicago, Illinois.
Bibliography
1. "In Memory of Charles Goodrich Hammond and Charlotte Bradley Hammond". (Cambridge: Riverside Press, 1887), 4-10.
2. Baird, Spencer Fullerton. Blatchford Family Papers - Additions, 1841-1947, Bulk 1870-1914., 1870.
3. Wikipedia contributors, "Eliphalet Wickes Blatchford," Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia, https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Eliphalet_Wickes_Blatchford&oldid=1047922605 (accessed December 3, 2021).
Correspondence.; Obituaries.; Biography.; Photographs.; Blatchford, E.W. (Eliphalet Wickes), 1826-1914; Hammond, Charles G.; Hammond, H. L. (Henry Laurens), 1815-1893
- Biographies of General Lewis Cass, 1843, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Autobiographical sketch of Charles G. Hammond, circa 1876 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Notes and research, 1876 1906; 1876-1906 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Charles and Charlotte Hammond photographs, 1877, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence between E.W. Blatchford and Hammond family, 1877 1900; 1877-1900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Funeral planning for Charles G. Hammond, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Obituaries and Tributes, 1884 1905; 1884-1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Charles G. Hammond memorial draft, 1899 1904; 1899, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondences with photographers, 1903 1906; 1903-1906 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondences, 1909 1913; 1909-1913 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Photographs related to Charles G. Hammond, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)